welcome to meditating with John robic II
I'm a cognitive psychologist and a
cognitive scientist at the University of
Toronto where academically and
scientifically study research and teach
about mindfulness and related phenomena
like Insight flow mystical experience
awakening experience higher states of
consciousness the cultivation of wisdom
in the aspiration towards enlightenment
I've also been practicing the pasta
meditation meta contemplation Tai Chi
Chuan for over 29 years and teaching
them professionally for close to 20
years welcome this is a progressive
course each Monday as a Dharma day and
on that day I give I teach people
practices and principles that build on
previous practices and principles I have
already taught them if you're joining
for the first time welcome but this is
the tenth lesson and it's the
culminating lesson in the introductory
course so if you want to go back and
learn everything that proceeded and led
up to it please look for links to
previous lessons on previous six in the
description of this video
Tuesday through Friday we meet at 9:30
est we all we regularly meet on Mondays
at least 9:30 est you as well
just today there was a scheduling
conflict so Tuesday through Friday we
meet we sit I review the principles a
couple of times in the practices at the
end of every Monday through Friday
sitting there is a Q&A please keep your
questions today right for this practice
these set of practices that are teaching
you for more comprehensive and broader
questions about maybe Buddhism in
general or Buddhism in stoicism at the
cultivation of wisdom or what does this
have to do with mystical experiences or
a whole host of questions there's two
things you can do one is please come to
the live Q&A I do every third Friday
I'll be do
on this Friday live streamed on YouTube
at 3 p.m. est so this Friday which I
believe is the 53 p.m. yesterday the
other thing you can do is subscribe to
my channel my video channel and that
will put you in touch with all kinds of
lectures and discussions about these
broader topics that are pursued in depth
if you get a chance please like this
video stream it will raise its bill of
visibility on the YouTube algorithm and
that will help me to reach out to as
many people as possible to give them
this valuable set of practices that can
help in this difficult time and also
more long-term with their life as a
whole
alright I think that's it for
announcements so let's get to the derma
so what I want to teach you today is
we're not it's it's it's it's the
culmination of the introductory course
the 10-week introductory course and Wow
we've made it a we're here we are the
tenth lesson and it's it's kind of
liminal that's what I guess what I want
to say it I put it here because it is
the capstone but it's also the thing
that bridges you into more advanced
practice so this is a practice you
should start doing and I'll explain how
to schedule it in in a few minutes but
if this is the practice that really its
growth depends on how all the other
practices underneath it are growing so
it grows very very slowly as you can
imagine so you have to be extremely
patient and take a big-picture view with
respect to what I'm going to teach you
so what I'm going to teach you is a
progeny practice this this is also known
as a non-duality practice so Praja right
it means wisdom right but it means a
particular kind of wisdom
it means sort of self liberated
intelligence but not intelligence in
sort of the the the holding of
propositions or belief but the ability
to see right through illusion and into
what's real and to be able to unlock the
world in your identity
in such a way that you are much more
appropriately fitted to it I'm thinking
about what why a wise person can do not
so much necessarily that they have a lot
of factual knowledge although that can
help what happens is they can come into
a situation and very dynamically and
think about mindfulness being connected
they are very mindfully connected to
themselves to the situation and to other
people involved in this situation and
they know how to in all this tangled
ill-defined mess zero in on the relevant
information and not just see it but also
right Co identified what they think of
Mehta
so that they are most appropriately
fitted to it and you have that and you
have that kind of self liberating
intelligence insight capacity that's and
so it's not we don't have a single word
in English that captures it really well
this way I like to use the Sanskrit term
Praja that it's it's an enacted dynamic
right wisdom that is realized in an
enhanced capacity to see through self
deceptive behavior and to connect to the
world in a deep and adaptive manner
it's where the we it's what results are
you November I study where you're the
Eightfold Path you have all these rights
like right understanding better you know
right vision right aspiration when the
right isn't moral right it's it's it's
the dexterity of the right hand it's
getting an optimal grip on things if you
remember so that's what progeny is
progeny is sort of having a
comprehensive flowing optimal grip in
all situations now of course that won't
be this that became your permanent
second nature that might in fact be one
way of thinking of what it would need to
be a blamed what we are looking for is
first of all how can we train it and how
can we bring it much more into our
awareness so that's very sort of a
philosophical and abstract let's make it
a little bit more concrete let's go back
to one of our primary metaphors remember
we talked about you know normally we
were looking through the mind
we're always framing the world in a
certain way for grounding
on things background the other things
creating patterns of salience how things
stand out to us and as we've talked
about that repeatedly this framing is
often completely transparent to us we're
doing it automatically mindlessly
reactively but what we can do with with
the pasa is we can learn to step back
and look at that framing become aware of
the patterns and processes of our mind
and notice anything that might be a
potential distortion get more clarity
about it bring more acuity to it all
that stuff we've been practicing and
then how do I know if I've actually
corrected the distortion well then I I
have to put my glasses back on
and like in Metta I have to look deeply
into the world and see if I can see the
world anew if I can unlock right my
identities and the identities of things
if I can turn my existential mode into
the being mode in which I in the world
are being reciprocally opened like you
do when you're falling in love with
somebody this is a kind of love of
course this is not sexual erotic love
this is the kind of love that is
captured by ruler words like Karuna
compassion right the word compassion is
a little bit problematic we'll come back
to that a little bit later when we move
on to some further lessons so this is
what you do in an insight insight has
sort of three components to it there is
a movement that breaks an inappropriate
frame and then there's a movement that
makes a more encompassing more
well-fitted more right-handed more
dexterous more octave leak gripping
frame and so when you're actually
studying insight as a phenomena you know
when you have an aha moment and I do
that scientifically at U of T it's made
up of these sort of three - what are the
three components there's a breaking
frame and the making frame and then
there's the flexibility to move between
them so breaking frame making frame and
how flexible are you in being able to do
that transfer me
so what does that mean in practice what
leans in practice that we want to do
something that's going to get those two
motions at work in a coordinated fashion
and that is training the flexibility
between them by having us constantly
flip and reverse between them that's how
you do flexibility you constantly
reverse your direction right you try to
extend the range and the fluency and the
speed of your ability to reverse
direction okay so this is what we're
going to do now okay I'm going to
describe this practice to you don't
start doing it right now and I also want
to give you some things to look for and
both positively like things that help
you sort of understand what's going on
and then also negatively things to watch
out for to avoid now for about 80% of
the people I've been teaching this for a
long time the way I'm going to describe
it works for them about 20% of the
people it's reversed they have to do it
the opposite way and so you're gonna
have to also experiment with this a
couple sets to see which one takes treat
so for the statistically normal group
this is what it's like as you inhale and
you feel your abdomen expanding you do
that extension of awareness outward in
Metta when you try and take Metta as
sort of broadly to maybe you've been
doing it towards all people not maybe
towards all being and right in a nut and
it's like flow not just broadly but
deeply you try to extend it towards all
beings and really unlock the potential
of the world to be other than use
currently see it as it's a kind of
insight and then as you exhale you do
the past nut and you do that but Pastner
that I taught you where you try and go
to the very center right that space
between your thoughts the silent morning
so you move towards sort of the
mysterious ground of the psyche in the
pasta and opening up to the mysterious
round of the world in meta and then what
you're doing
is flowing between them you're flowing
between them so like so for 80% of the
people as you inhale Mehta out as you
exhale the pasta end to a space between
your thoughts now the flexibility will
be lacking right so what does that mean
well you'll you'll say in half a breath
I won't get much better that's right
that's right
and in half of a breath I won't will I
be able to get most of that know you
better than to just going to move
towards it flexibility means and this is
what will take a lot of time just to get
the flexibility is that you know the
inhale you're able to realize deep Mehta
and in the exhale you're able to realize
deep focus now this takes time you're
not initially flexible so you will only
get a shallow sense of meta and a
shallow sense of a Pastner that is fine
that will take time it's fine that will
take time now in connection with that
here's something to avoid in order to
extend the time so so that they have
more time to try to get deeper into meta
and deeper and the pasta people start to
hyperventilate exaggerating so you know
what I mean it's very very important
this practice is the one that is most
susceptible to hyperventilation and it
would make you lightheaded it's not good
for you so you have to be vigilant that
you are not hyperventilating you have to
leave your breathing alone and let it
flow naturally you want this you want
Prussia to be something that flows
naturally in you not something that only
is arrived at when you force things to
an extremity okay so
really andar really accepting that this
was going to initially be I don't have
the flexibility so initially shallow
meta shallow of a Pastner just whatever
taste I can get of both and now I
hyperventilate not hyperventilate
you'll do this for a long time for a
long time all you're going to be doing
is developing the flexibility now notice
that Praja is only as good as you are
practicing meta and deep the pasta and
trying to extend that a little bit
farther by the way like if you've only
been going up to like people maybe all
sentient beings and then after a while
more beings okay so it's very crucial
that what you just the the progress that
you're looking for initially is just
that in a natural unforced breath I can
move into deep meta so you I have to be
practicing meta a lot and I have to be
doing this a lot before it that will
occur and then in the out-breath I get
into deep for pasta right so I have to
be practicing the pasta a lot deep
Vipassana and practicing this progeny
practice a lot before that will happen
so that's going to take a long time
once they there they both are deep
alright then you'll just be there for a
while just getting the flexibility to
become very second nature that flow then
what starts to happen is you start to
get a foreground background so well I'm
sensing meta I have sort of a background
awareness of the depth of a past know
that I was touching and then it goes
like this it starts to go like this and
then I start to be able to feel them
both active in my breath this takes a
long time and then it's all at once
simultaneously as deeply out and is
deeply in mystery to mystery ground to
ground the deepest possible reciprocal
opening the deepest residence
you're in the state right of non-duality
your awareness is not subjectively
oriented or objectively oriented it's
transient it this is the place that is
optimal for optimizing your optimal grip
for affording deep deep insight not just
intellectual insight but insight at the
very level of the identity of yourself
and the world this is a fundamentally
liberating form of intelligence inside
Praja
this will not be something that happens
to you tomorrow next week next month
maybe not even this year okay this takes
a long time before it comes in that's
what I mean when I said this practice is
liminal you can start it with with an
introductory set of skills if you have
to start somewhere but you will go
through these stages for a very long
time all you will be doing is the
developing the flexibility then you will
start to develop some of the
simultaneity and then you will get the
gestalt of possible and then more and
more as you practice that it will be
there available to you and it will start
to present itself to you so now you
should think of yourself having this
kind of practice always one day do basic
start with basics of house nut basic
bypass not and then lead into deeper
past my next day do meta trying always
and gradually to be extending meta third
day Praja do that twice see good three
and three
okay but that's not basic into deep meta
deepening it Praja
and then again the past of a second too
deep meta deepening it and Praja
the seventh day do one of the other
things like perhaps meditative questing
in order to refine and enhance inquiring
mindfulness okay so that's the practice
don't rush into it I recommend doing
some you know basically passing the
first reminding yourself satyed enacted
remembering oh yeah this is what the
pastor feels like then a bit of meta
perhaps your most extensive meta that
you have been practicing regularly and
push it up remember not just as wide as
possible but as deep you're trying to
really do as much reciprocal opening
remembering the being mode as much as
you can just a metaphor a while and then
come back to the pasta and do the deeper
pasta space between your thoughts and
then in breath deep meta out breath
deeper pasta accepting that it will be
shallow not as deep as when I can sit on
within eat four with each for a long
time and not hyperventilating so we'll
sit for about 15 minutes maybe you know
after you've done your Center and
routine you know to two or three minutes
I'm gonna time you through it just to do
it intuitively right a few minutes you
know basic you know basic in the pasta
then deep meta returning to deep for
pasta and then go into Praja don't
hyperventilate don't hyperventilate
don't hyperventilate understand that the
meta and a half breath and of a past and
a half breath rather be much shallower
than when you can follow them completely
with a whole breath for a complete 15
minutes it takes a long time to develop
the flexibility okay
so take your time be patient
make sure your phones are set on - do
not disturb it's your posture ready and
we will begin when I say together begin
Shh slowly come out of you practice
trying as best you can get integrate
what he cultivated in your practice with
your Bhatia consciousness and cognition
perhaps by reciting the five promises to
yourself
all right everyone so we went a little
bit long today there don't seem to be
any questions though um are there any
questions that need to be addressed okay
so maybe I gave you a lot to think about
that's great and so we'll pick up the
questions tomorrow please remember
please remember that I need your help
like this video to raise its visibility
on YouTube stream please subscribe to
the channel so you can be notified of
videos you can become aware of I said a
whole bunch of extra videos that will
and you know there's both the lectures
from awakening from the meaning crisis
and there's all the discussions with
voices with rebecky where all of this is
pursued and with much more depths and
detail and much more comprehensively I
want to thank you for joining I want to
thank my dear friend and techno mae
Jamar and my beloved son Jason please
invite others who might benefit from
this to share in this remember we're
going back on our original schedule
tomorrow back at 9:30 est finally
remember continuity of practice is more
important than quantity there is no
enemy worse than your own mind there is
no ally no friend greater than your own
mind take care everyone
keep practicing we'll see you tomorrow
morning